welcome to meditating genre of achy we
live stream every weekday morning at 9
30 a.m
eastern time with mondays alternating
between a new lesson called dharma day
and a review of the whole ecology of
practices which is called a pie a day
there'll be no there'll be no stream
next wednesday
due to scheduling conflicts if you're
joining us for the first time
you're most welcome previous lessons and
sits see the description
and what i recommend you do is do the
first lesson and then start joining us
every day
and then once or twice a week do another
one of the lessons and you will very
quickly
integrate with the community please like
the stream to increase the visibility of
the youtube algorithm
at the end of every set there is
q a please limit the questions
at that time to questions from anywhere
in the whole ecology of practices
for more general questions please join
me today for the general
livestream q a on youtube at 3 pm
eastern time
i think that's everything we need to do
to get
ready uh we'll begin as always with
chanting
and um then we'll go into the silent set
and we'll have
a nice chunk of time to get to some
questions please remember that in a
dedication to questions
uh comments and sharing are really um
also
important uh to the lifeblood of this
community
all right everyone so set your phones on
do not disturb
let's get into position and we will
begin when i say begin
begin
[Music]
oh
one
[Music]
oh
one
[Music]
oh
one
[Music]
begin your silences
slowly commodity practice trying as best
you can to integrate with cultivated in
your practice with your everyday
consciousness cognition
character and communicates perhaps by
reciting the five promises
to himself
oh good we have some a bit of time for
some questions that's excellent
i look forward to these questions a lot
i look forward to uh hopefully uh many
of you can come
this afternoon at 3 pm eastern time
especially if you have more encompassing
questions
this is from ionis is it necessary to
take short inhales during the chant
or can or can one have a longer and
deeper inhales and exhales
um you can take longer and slower
inhales
and exhales if you wish
so but that's one of the difficulties
that we're doing it virtually
because when people do it as a group
they sort of in this self-organizing
fashion get into a rhythm of inhaling
inhalation and exhalation i can't hear
you guys doing that so
i just fall into the pattern when i do
what i'm chanting on my own but
don't take that to be sort of you know a
very rigid
representation of the pattern of
breathing that needs to be
engaged in when you're doing the
chanting whatever
engages the musicality uh the
physicality the embodiment
like the invocation of emergence in ohm
and of uh emanation in one whatever does
that for you reliably
then pattern your breathing according to
that toggle
everything as you seek out the
aspiration to enlightenment
kira kroger hi kara it was so good uh
getting to
meet you face to face virtually uh the
other day
uh yesterday i guess so that was a great
pleasure
i hope you enjoyed uh the time at that
conference
uh rave kelly put together an amazing
conference on movement
um and how it contributes to a
meaningful life movement practices
and in connection with that uh this
monday on dharma day
i'm going to teach you tai chi walking
which is a form of walking meditation
and then i'll
add in as the week goes on we'll add in
arm movements and you'll get
a sequence of tai chi called brush news
and so we're going to be bringing in a
little bit more movement
in as well sorry kira we should get to
your question now
often when i do inquiring mindfulness
i'll get a movie reference to a
character
often say my unconscious talks to me in
movies i think my question is
what do i do with that so that's
excellent um
i think that's very normal for many of
us
in the practice keep going but take note
of that character
and you might want to uh
then take that into another practice
which i have not talked too much about
a kind of active imagination a jungian
practice
in which um you would invoke that
character
uh in imagery and then try to let it be
spontaneously animated
by um i guess information communication
from the unconscious
and then try to interact dialogically uh
with it
and so that can be a powerful way of
trying to open up the channel i
recommend that while you're doing the
inquiring mindfulness
you still treat that as another valuable
uh portal that you're grateful to and
you step beyond
to step through but um
this is also a symbol on a symbol
symbol on means to join two things
together the conscious and the
unconscious
that is potentially present uh present
to you
and then so taking up something like the
open mindedness which we'll
talk about because it's basically a
theoretical neoplatonic practice we'll
talk about that
when we do the wisdom of hypatia um but
that
that you might you could probably go
online and find a couple
make sure it's by somebody who has
training in union therapy
uh some stuff on how to do active
imagination there's some books
you might want to take that character
into active imagination as a way
of affording more symbolic discourse
between your conscious and unconscious
mind like they said we will come back to
that
uh later when we get in more depth um
i'm sorry i keep promising you all these
practices but
we will get to them and you can see how
they complement see how naturally
they complement what we're doing in this
in in these
eastern oriented practices so that's a
suggestion here
for now and like i said by the time you
get into the wisdom of hypatia
that's something uh we'll be able to uh
pursue it more in depth all of us
together and hopefully
uh you'll be able to ask some more
penetrating
uh questions at that time dimitar
how do i use a journal to cultivate my
buddha in a period where i have no
insights to write down
what do i write about so uh when you
when you don't have
insights um well you probably do
you're just not realizing it but um many
of them are not full blown aha
experiences
uh you may just notice something about
somebody that you hadn't noticed before
or you might when you realize that
you're you've caught yourself from
distraction throughout the day
and you come back moments of mindfulness
are very
important moments moments also when you
felt
um that you stepped outside of being
locked into that sort of
hurt hunger fever framing of egocentrism
when you had a genuine impulse of
generosity
or caring for another person it will
probably very quickly
get permeated and twisted by
egocentrism that that sets all of us but
don't get don't get don't get frustrated
or don't fall into despair about that
there if there is nevertheless if there
was not actually a genuine moment
of generosity and outreach the machinery
of egocentrism wouldn't have to swoop in
so powerfully
to constrain and control it so try to
take note of that try to take
note of those moments and so try to
think of it a continuum from
all the way up to sort of full-blown aha
almost epiphany insights
down to little moments of noticing
mindfulness noticing a difference
noticing perhaps a change in your
orientation toward things
and especially moments of generosity
outreach
what's called ecstasis in the
neoplatonic tradition standing beyond
yourself
those moments when you are genuinely uh
even for a moment before that other
machinery gets it
right you're beyond yours you're beyond
yourself
uh so take note of all of those it may
be also
um uh in an aesthetic experience when
you're in music
you may realize sometimes that you get
caught up ecstatically beyond it
note that remember it instead of just
letting it uh drift away
into the half dream of memory
i can't quite read it here that it's
it's either
or please forgive me if i'm
mispronouncing it
occur observation watching how air was
moving
uh the leaves on the plant outside i
observed some amazing synchronous
degrees with my thoughts and perception
this is the first time i want to do
again thanks again john
um so what tends to happen and this is
this is something you have to treat very
very carefully
as you get into these practices as you
start to get reciprocal
opening happening as we've talked about
you you there will be more
of these called synchronicities
sort of uh things happen where there
seems to be
a resonant correspondence between what's
going on inside and outside
um and this is very tempting and i think
perhaps to some degree even young pal
created this temptation
to get into sort of thinking of this
magically
and that it gives us sort of a secret
way which we could manipulate things
i'm not i'm not saying you're doing that
i'm just saying that this is something
we need
remember what the buddha said the buddha
was very not very specific about what
you needed to do in order to be
a disciple a follower but he said this
is how you know
someone is not one of my disciples when
they offer to perform a miracle
so right noticing those synchronicities
is something that you could write in
your journal and celebrate
but it's very important
to resist an inflationary impulse that
comes up very naturally
when those kinds of resonances occur
so that's just some overall values there
that's definitely something to note in
your journal
note it as an indication that reciprocal
opening
is probably occurring but remember to
frame it in a non-inflationary manner
i mean what we're ultimately after in
some ways
this is a neoplatonic way of putting it
is we're after non-inflationary
identification with what which is what
with what is most ultimate
the great temptation and this is in so
much mythology about the evil sorcerer
is as we as that starts to occur
we snap it back inside our ego-centric
framing
and we try to swallow the ultimate into
ourselves
a form of blasphemy and idolatry
that is deeply destructive of everything
we're trying to realize
in our aspirations towards wisdom and
enlightenment
if you start to lose
you start to lose the sense of your
mortality
your mortality isn't the fact that
you're going to die
it's in the first mark noble truth your
mortality is that there is no area of
your life
no part of your psyche that is not
susceptible to dukkha not susceptible to
self-deception
that to remember your mortality is to
remember no matter where you turn
you are limited by that perennial threat
and that right and it's very easy to
start forgetting that
when we start to because it is truly
wonderful joseph pickens
hello joseph uh it's good to uh have you
here and asking questions what should
the mind be doing during the moving
uh uh so the gender is the sitting ones
when you're moving so if you're doing
any of these so this is the taoist
there's a yin and yang so in the
movements
what you're generally doing is there's
an opening and closing of the body
in some fashion and then you're doing
the same thing with your mind so
when i'm opening my hands for example
this is like meta
and i'm opening up my attention out
towards
the horizon that encompasses me and then
as i close
my hands this is so this is yang
and then this is the yin movement this
is the movement towards the center
that ultimately grounds me so
opening up to the horizon that
accompanies
accompanies me moving towards what's
called the axis mundi the
the axis of the world the center that
grounds me
so my mind is moving yang
and yin with the moving practices
uh uh k conoloy i've always had a song
i always have a song running through my
mind when i try to meditate do you have
any tips to deal with this
um so that's
very often the case trying to do
something about it
is the thing that will mo will make it
worse
so is it possible to
leave it in this position what i do and
it seems to work for me
is i just i don't treat it as an
obstacle
i try to get it so that it's in
the background and periphery of my
awareness
where it just runs and then what i've
noticed is
if i can get to that place where i'm not
fighting it
i'm also not indulging it just it's
there
and i treat it almost like you know you
go into a temple
and there's music off in some room
people are chanting
i'm just meditating here and they're off
there and this is a part of my mind
chanting
you know it's often some other room and
what happens is that
that really fades in its ability to sort
of
get it get a grip on my awareness
sometimes if it fades into silence
uh sometimes it just diminishes but i
found that has been very helpful for me
uh for dealing with that kind of inner
music
karima sharing an observation thank you
uh for sharing observations
observation i began speaking meta aloud
to begin with and
during when mine began watering found it
powerful and good to keep focused
a few distractions used to be safe well
and happy and free from suffering
peaceful
then deepened with suchness and mourners
finally sent from my heart
without words that's meta yet that's
fantastic karina thank you for sharing
that
that the way that happens um i believe
you were also there yesterday i believe
i saw you i don't think i got to speak
to you
um so yeah um that that sort of out of
speaking and then it's very analogous to
alexio divina and the way it became more
and more
um internalized and more and more
soulful with the suchness and muchness
until it finally moves to a wordless
thing
yeah that that's fantastic thank you for
sharing that
um that's that that con and when that
happens sort of
naturally that unfolds that progression
very very powerful
very very helpful april rubenstein
hi gabriel observation after the answer
you gave to my question last week
thanks made a real breakthrough in
vipassana
i was on a high for the rest of the day
i felt able to tap into the dynamic
round of my mind easily
it's good after that strangely a mild
depression set in for a couple days
yes this has now subsided but i think on
some level
i was imagining my meditation would give
me magical powers yes
and the quantum leap in my progress
disillusioned me
somehow yeah that's exactly right uh uh
gabriel that's exactly right that goes
to what i was talking earlier about
how these epiphanic ecstatic moments um
they they are like they are great right
um
like i said the day you will also have
because those are the big
frame making moments you'll also have
those periods of dryness
that are also important because they are
the periods of
uh frame breaking and very often you get
a rebound effect like you just described
we get this frame making but that
doesn't mean that the machinery
is all gone and then we have to go back
and do
frame breaking and we have to wrestle
with patterns
we're wrestling with a perennial problem
which is the temptation
right uh the temptation to inflation
so take part in the fact that you
recognized it
and you have gone through the the yang
and the yin and now you're getting the
the the the point of stabilization
between them dimitar
do you have any book recommendations or
online resources you can point to for
guidance on practicing and internalizing
active open-mindedness
um
i do um hang on sorry i'm gonna have to
go off camera
uh this is odd i know but just hang on
for a second i'm going to try and get
that book
as i said we will come back uh to this
in more detail when we come to the
theory of part
of neoplatonic practice so a very good
book for
engaging in active open-mindedness is
imagination a space of freedom
i particularly like the subtitle
dialogue between the ego and the
unconscious
this is by varina cast uh k-a-s-t
and this is a book on how to start
practicing
active imagination
here's a good book for sort of
background
uh understanding and material on it uh
called encounters with the soul active
imagination as developed by cj young
by barbara barbara hannah
and then i recommend it's a very famous
book
supplementing that with the book by
gentleman
g-e-n-d-l-i-n called focusing
which is a good way to sort of making
this practice more embodied
as a practice
so i hope that's helpful also any
similar resources for logical reasoning
and argumentation
i'm not going to go off camera again
dimitar i will uh
give you uh something similar to that um
when we get into stoicism with the with
the wisdom of hypatia
and we'll learn how to uh bring aspects
of that in
um sort of in a socratic fashion i do
recommend
these previous videos where i've
recommended that what you need to do
first before you do that
is you need to start cultivating active
open-mindedness get the books on the
cognitive biases
read one a day just try to note it at
the end of the day don't push yourself
let it
permeate and percolate and you'll
cultivate active open-mindedness
you need to really situate any attempt
to improve
uh logic and argumentation within the
virtue of active open-mindedness
there's a lot of argument and evidence
behind what i just said so
it's a very important point
the sun came out in sweden today i found
myself lost in the raids while naturally
applying some of our practice
without aiming to do that it was a
simple and magnificent experience
for that i am very grateful thank you
thank you for sharing that
that's what i mean about when right when
it spontaneously comes up
right what's what when the patterns and
principles in your practice
spontaneously start to come up in your
life in your your everyday experience
that's when the integration is occurring
that's when that's a moment in which
your buddha nature your inner sage
is starting to take on a life of its own
thank you for sharing that that's deeply
encouraging to all of us
so everyone thank you for joining today
i hope to see you again this afternoon
at 3 p.m if you can make it
i want to thank my dear friend and
techno major maher my beloved son jason
who's always behind the scenes pinch
hitting
please subscribe to this channel to be
notified of the next video
you'll also find links to the lecture
series awakening from the meaning crisis
the the dialogue series our voices with
verveiki
in which uh some of the main themes of
this course
are related are discussed and related to
other themes and situated within a more
encompassing context please invite
others who might benefit by joining
joining this series uh brad is here
pleasure of the doubt
pleasure of doubt i should say uh so
please join the discord server
to chat with others to sit with others
do the moving uh meditation practice i
believe you got moving practices
um i think you're also chanting together
also to get into excellent uh
dialogue and discussion i strongly uh
uh encourage uh the discord server to
again home the senga
this upcoming wednesday
we're doing this every weekday morning
at 9 30 eastern time
as i just mentioned however we will not
be doing it next wednesday
due to scheduling difficulties please
remember
that continuity of practice is more
important than your quantity of practice
there is no enemy worse than your own
minded body but there's no friend no
ally no true companion on the path
better than your own mind and body
be lamps unto yourselves and to each
other
take care everyone see you on monday
hopefully some of you
this afternoon bye
you